hello welcome everyone it's January 29th
2025 we're in active inference guest
stream
97.1 with Dr Matthew Sims discussing a
cellular slime mold a jumping off point
for exploring different Notions of
biological memory so thank you for
joining looking forward to hearing more
thanks so much hello welcome everyone
it's January 2 2025 we're in
returning in 1 second thank
you we're back back like a slime mold
returning we're back should I start or
should I should we just go for it yeah
yeah begin begin from the beginning of
the presentation thank you I I can't
hear you oh thank you we're back go for
it okay sorry about
that um so yeah uh today I'm going to be
looking
at a couple of questions
regarding uh feran polyam
which is a cellular slime mold and I'm
going to be looking at uh different
Notions of memory that have been thought
about in the biological sciences not
necessarily in for example when you're
thinking about large language models or
when you're thinking about computational
memory outside of biological systems but
uh biological memory and pheran polyam
is a kind of is a springboard if you
will for thinking about things like this
now this uh organism I'm going to get a
little bit into its
biology uh and a little bit into kind of
it's It's its complex life cycles and
these are these are different things
that I I kind of uh have researched and
uh thought about in in in the kind of
more recent book that I've uh published
with Cambridge University press called
slim molden philosophy uh and this
particular talk that you'll see right
now is going to be uh kind of an excerpt
if you will from a couple of the
chapters namely chapter three of the
book
uh and looking at memory I think it's a
quite nice uh way to get to get to get a
kind of an overall understanding of the
importance of this this system this
model system and it's a system that's
becoming used more and more to
investigate various questions uh in
either cognitive science or in ecology
or in or in philosophy biology or
theoretical biology more generally uh
questions like uh biological
individuality for example questions like
uh you know uh the the the biological or
the biological status of of something
like a Spore dormant Spore uh when we're
thinking about living systems being
systems that are more generally systems
that are metabolically active so what
does that mean if life is you have a
form of life that's not metabolically
active and looking at the biology of
something like uh pheran polylon or
slime mold can really I I think it's
very kind of instrumental into digging
into these questions more theoretical
questions and also you can explore and
expand upon these questions by
generating hypothesis that can be really
tested in a organism that's quite easy
to culture uh so this
talk uh is going to proceed as follows
with that kind of
background um I'm going to look at what
ferum is then I'm going to turn to a
really really really beautiful
experiment it's a very interesting and
Powerful experiment experiment welld
designed by Chris Reed uh and colleagues
uh at MC University uh they're still
they're still doing experiments with
ferum uh and this particular experiment
is is about kind of externalized memory
in phum uh I'll look at that experiment
go through it then I'll look at
different forms of biological
memory uh and these different forms of
biological memory I'm going to cap it
out at three or four different forms of
biological memory and try to connect
them
um and then I'm going to ask a question
regarding uh whether or
not one of one or more of these forms of
biological memory requires uh an
explanation uh using kind of cognitive
theories or cognitive
Frameworks uh and I'm going to answer
that question uh using the notion of
metabolic individuality it's a again
it's biological individuality which
we'll get into during the talk also
and so applying this particular type of
Criterion from biological individuality
or metabolic individuality as a
Criterion I'm going to be able to kind
of rule out which
levels uh of memory depending upon the
levels of biological organization that
these this memory happens in uh are you
know the the warranted targets of
cognitive
explanation
so uh what's pheran polyon so pher
polyam uh uh it's it's the the Latin
name the the genus is for zeram um and
polyam is the kind of the species the
species name the species addon and that
generally means uh you know many headed
and they say this many-headed in the
sense that it's a many uh the Spore
comes out of a what looks like to be a
many headed uh Fring body uh generally
it's an it's an acellular slime mold uh
it's a protest a unicellular protest and
it has a very interesting complex life
cycle and when I say complex life cycle
what I mean is that uh it has it's m has
multi faets it's multifaceted in a sense
that um it has more than one vegetative
stage one the one than more stage where
it actually has a form that reproduces
and and kind of uh you know forges
eats uh and this stage goes from a
Spore uh at number one the Spore
actually germinates and out from the
Spore you have something called
a a bif flatulate cell or a mix amiba
cell now uh a mix amoeba comes out of
the Spore it germinates from the Spore
When there's less water in the
environment the bif flatulate actually
is something that
is the kind of the fella are going to be
something that's synthesized when
there's more water in the area when it
uh germinates now uh during a mix amoeba
stage it can
reproduce asexually uh so there are many
many different kind of clones clone
cells and each of these have a single
nucleus uh one it actually encounters
another type another mix amoeba of the
same uh the same type not necessarily
genetically the same uh they can
actually come together and this when you
have that's when you have a type of
reproduction that occurs it's
uh uh mosis without actually uh cell
separation so without cyto Kinesis and
that's when you start having this
particular growth of a cell and these
are all these are all microscopic small
single cells uh until this stage where
the nucle reproduce and it starts
growing and becomes uh visible to the
eye and this is becomes a plasmo stage
this plasmodial stage is the stage at
which uh most of the experiments with
ferum occur uh and uh it's it's it's
very interesting stage because this at
this stage uh the ferum the cell again
it's a single cell multinuclear single
cell uh crawls over and locomotes over
various
surfaces you can design experiments
watching this particular type of
locomotion now again I talked about the
veget ative
stage
uh I've said pretty much this during
this vegetative stage um pum uh during
this plasmodial stage it's going to
consume bacteria fungi and decaying
organic matter and again here you have a
a a picture from one of my lab
experiments of AUM just uh locomoting
and covering
oats uh during this plasmodial stage or
the vegetative stage one of its
vegetative stages uh there's again many
experiments that have shown interesting
types of capacities that it
displays it's been uh shown to kind of
solve the shortest path problem uh
engage in habituation which is a type of
learning very simple type of learning
anticipate periodic environmental
conditions hot bursts of
Air dve Bursts of air excuse me and uh
make flexible behavioral decisions that
are based upon compar to valuation rules
rather than absolute
valuation um and this is just um you
know a very very brief summary of the
various experiments that have been uh
that ferum has been used with to engage
in questions regarding things like
learning things like decision- making
and there many more experiments but you
get a a kind of representation of what
this might
be now let's move on with that kind of
brief understanding of what uh you know
the life cycle of his Aram is and
focusing upon this particular type of uh
vegetative stage the plasmodial stage we
can start thinking about one experiment
in particular the experiment by Chris
Reed and his lab over at mccre in
2012 now uh you'll see a particular you
know picture here of Hansel and grle and
I hope to make this clear why I'm
showing this to you
um so when pher when it when it
locomotes over
surfaces it leaves an extracellular SL
slime trace or slime Trail I refer to
this as es now es is um it's a poly
polymus saccharide and it's a this
this this mucus uh makes it easier for
for zerum to actually locomote but it
serves many many
functions and uh it's been well known in
the
literature since the 50s that wherever
ferum uh you know wherever it navigates
wherever it locomotes it leaves this
trail behind it so one question that has
risen uh and a question that is kind of
uh the Crocs of the experiment for rad
Al is whether or not pum uses this
extracellular SL to navigate so the
reason why I they can ask this question
has been observed that feram avoid their
own extracellular slime Trails uh and
the extracellular Slime Trails of
others now if it's used as a type of
externalized spatial memory uh avoiding
you know expending energy unnecessarily
to revisit patches of food again food is
being uh bacteria food being fungus uh
other types of
microorganisms uh if you can use that to
avoid previously forged patches uh then
this is this becomes an interesting type
of relationship with a particular type
of poly mucus
mucopolysaccharide right and so to test
this uh they have a couple conditions
two conditions so they have an AAR
plate uh and this agar plate is the
conditions are exactly the same except
for except for one
one plate of agar is covered with
extracellular slime the other isn't the
covered uh plate is called the the coda
condition and the blank the other is the
blank condition they set a u shaped
acetate trap on this particular plate uh
and the whole idea is to put ferum as
you see in a start Zone and put a goal
which is going to be a drop of highly
concentrated
glucose and that go is food
so
if uh feram is going to actually use
extracellular slime to
navigate and to avoid you know
navigating in areas on the on the AAR
that it's already navigated on uh the
hypothesis is that in the coded
Condition it's going to take a lot
longer and that's exactly what they
found it took about 10 times uh the the
the time actually 10 it was 10 times
greater uh in the in the coded condition
in the non-quota
condition so they come back to this idea
and here you have kind of the Hans grle
element uh as uh Reed Al kind of make
the following conclusion I said the
results of this study I provide a unique
demonstration of spatial memory systems
and non-al organisms supporting the
theory that an externalized spatial
memory may be the functional precursor
of an internal memory of higher
organisms I think this is quite
interesting the two hypothesis obviously
and I think one can safely ignore one of
the hypothesis and concentrate on the
the the kind of formal hypothesis about
an externalized spatial memory
system uh whether or not that system uh
was a precursor to uh internal lives
memory that's something
else
now in this particular type of uh
conclusion based upon this experiment
memory processes have been and and this
externalized memory process has been you
know interpreted as a particular type of
cognitive process albeit one that
extends into the environment now is that
strange May yeah sure one up it it is
strange but really I think there's a lot
of at least for the last 20 to 30 years
there's been a lot of uh uh you know a
lot of research done and focused upon
the idea of what's called you know the
the hypothesis of extended mind the
hypoth hypothesis of extended cognition
and uh you know my my PhD supervisor
Andy Clark he was very instrumental him
and Dave Charmers were very instrumental
in kind of putting that out there I
think that sometimes uh you know uh
cognition can be scaffolded by external
elements and I think this is that that's
fine I think uh if we take that if we
take that assumption on board it
shouldn't really matter whether or not
it's on the outside or on the inside but
we'll come back to this um
so now I want to think about in order to
actually really move on to the question
is this really memory
though uh which is a more fundamental
question uh to think about what memory
is so I'm taking a definition or
characterization as I like to call it a
rough characterization from uh Fran and
Mike lean and uh Mike and
look at memory as the follows in one of
the papers so they they say it's
experience dependent modification of
internal structure in a stimulus
specific manner that alters the way the
system is going to respond to a stimulus
in the future as a function of its past
now I think a couple things stand out in
this particular type of
characterization uh one is that it's
stimul is specific so breaking a bone
for example is not going to count as a m
there many ways to break a bone and it
doesn't then the breaking a bone is not
going to necessarily be dependent upon
uh one type of stimulus so that's a very
important element of this of this
definition uh another important element
which I'm pushing back on is the idea
that it has to be a modification of
internal
structure again if we take the
hypothesis of extended cognition
seriously uh there's no really there
there's no reason to be dependent upon
this assumption about internal structure
sometimes it
extends and that's an assumption that
I'm I'm willing to take on maybe some
people won't but that's something I
definitely I'm definitely willing to
take on depending upon the functional
kind of uh the functional analysis of
what's going on
here now putting this into place uh you
have a different type of
characterization so I think uh you can
add external structure here internal
structure or external structure now one
important thing also about uh Lev's B
Lev's characterization when they bring
this up they have a footnote which says
you know
memory uh is going to be outstripped in
terms
of uh that memory that's necessarily
associated with cognition necessarily
associated with intelligence so there's
going to be many more types of memory
than those that are necessarily
associated with intelligence or
cognition what does that mean that's
what we're going to get into next I
suppose uh so you have different forms
of biological memory that the ones that
I'm going to look over right now for
this presentation is uh these are going
to be dependent upon different levels of
biological organization different time
scales and biological levels of
organization now one is going to be
cellular memory which are individual
individual cells somatic cells for
example uh immunological memory networks
of cells and molecules so you're getting
larger larger time scale uh individual
organisms and then
Collective uh Collective memory or on a
collective scale a group of organisms
necessarily I'm going to look at the
notion of kind of colonal memory a
colonial
memory
um so what's cellular memory uh in a
nutshell which I'm sure many of you know
uh cellular memory is going to describe
how various PL poent cells uh you know
stem cells differentiate into different
types of cells uh and stem cells
themselves after they start actually
differentiating those cells
reproduce uh and as they reproduce they
don't go back to stem cells and then
turn back into for example a fat cell
the fat cells produce fat cells so
there's some type of way that cells
maintain the cellular type over mitosis
or cellular division and this is what uh
cellular memory can be understood
as uh one of the ways that this occurs
uh one of the mechanisms underlying this
again I hope this is not too um simplify
for everyone but uh I I think it's kind
of an important thing to talk about
anyway um is through epigenetic
modification and this is one of the ways
that kind of epigenetic uh markers uh
and epigenetic mechanisms uh were was
introduced biologically was looking
through or trying to understand the
question as to how differentiated cells
remain differentiated over time during
development during onogen
ontogenesis um and these epigenetic
mechanisms there many of them uh but a
couple of the ones that I have here just
kind of examples a histone
modification where you have uh you know
you have an
octomer uh of histones that are going to
be
wrapped uh by uh a particular type of
kind of strand of
DNA his stones are going to make up uh
these These histones are going to make
up uh the
chromatin and uh and going to make up
they're going to make up the
um the larger the larger groupings of
cells sorry sorry the larger groupings
of kind of DNA um and when hstone is
actually wrapped very tightly when the
DNA is wrapped very tightly around
hisone it's it can be accessed for the
uh for
transcription so what that means uh you
have some the brakes are put on to
transcriptions or the brakes are put on
uh in terms of uh uh genetic
processing which is okay so that acts in
and of itself as a type of memory and if
one is very interested in this one can
look into the work of kind of yeah you
say you Blanca and Avia Blanca and Maran
lamb they've done incredible research on
this uh philosophically and
biologically H but this is one of the
things that kind of in a nutshell
explains uh the way that a cell actually
when it differentiates Remains the Same
type of cell as the same type of cell
now you have hisy modification chromatin
marking uh RNA in interference there are
many different types of uh you
epigenetic mechanisms that can be used
but this is just an overview very quick
and inaccurate over you
probably uh moving on to the immune
system
memory now uh I think uh immunis Castro
says it best so I'm going to read this
out for you our immune system is
composed of a huge number of cells
presenting receptors on their
surfaces transmembrane receptors these
receptors are responsible for bonding
with portions of pathogens known as
antigens and signaling other immune
cells to eliminate the marked or
recognized
pathogens now uh this the invading
pathogens replicate themselves inside
our bodies thus increasing the amount of
damage being caused to our organism one
way the immune system evolved to fight
against infection was by replicating our
immune cell so as to cope with the
replicating pathogen but the replication
of immune cells is not perfect you have
errors you have mutations now errors
occur with a rate proportional to the
quality of recognition between immune
receptors
uh and the pathogen recognized those
mutated cells with high Affinity with
the pathogen High Affinity means that uh
they have in terms of their kind of uh
their shape they fit together well uh
they're selected maintain a repertoire
called
memory uh so to to just illustrate this
very
quickly uh you have certain cells with
transmembrane receptor which are kind of
represented by these different shapes
coming off these circles these cells and
they're going to fit better they're
going to have kind of um better
recognition with some of the foreign
antigens the ones with that are better
recognized and again uh they're going to
they're going to be the ones that are
put into a particular type of reservoir
and they mutate and the
mutation ends up actually making uh
trans membrane cell cell receptors or
cell transmembrane receptors that are
going to actually fit even better with
the pathogens and they're put in the
kind of kind of again this repertoire of
of memory cell memory or immunological
memory organismal memory is the thing
that everyone uh typically thinks about
particularly from the perspective of
psychology comparative psychology
cognitive science uh or even modeling so
um and this is just answering the
question is how an organism adapts to uh
via changing experiences adapts to a
changing world over the lifetime uh and
again it's over the lifetime that has to
be uh you know put forward uh the idea
that something like organismal memory
occurs
typically uh it's going to occur
typically over uh ontogenesis over over
a long trajectory of development from
from birth to death um so
uh the particular type of uh parag Matic
way of looking at memory and looking at
learning also I suppose uh people start
looking at this or scientists start
looking at it metazoa uh just because
cognitive science which is a very still
young young science uh in piggybacking
off of psychology has started with
humans and then thinking about other
types of uh Clos closely related animals
uh but now things are obviously changing
a little bit people are asking questions
as Chris Reed has asked questions about
memory and ferum uh but this is just a
little bit of the background and I'm not
going to say too much about organismal
memory because I think this comes uh
quite intuitively given the particular
type type of uh you know our approach to
memory and cognitive science
already um memory one thing that should
be said also is that typically it's
going to be associated with uh learning
so uh learning is the way that uh
memories are
encoded uh typically but this is
something that we can come back to later
which I think is interesting uh
particularly with vum but with other
organisms such as
acia now Collective memory the last type
of memory I'm going to talk
about um this refers to how H history
dependent self-organizing behavior of a
group of organisms become stabilized at
the level of the collective rather than
at the level of the individual that
makes up that
Collective and a lot of the research
that has been done on Collective
memory uh is the work on colonal memory
uh ant colonies for example or termite
colonies or um these typ these types of
insects that have uh you know use use
fairmon uh as a as a as a manner of uh
navigating a particular type of in a
spatial
environment
now uh Deborah Gordon she's is um a
fantastic
zoologist um and she was at Oxford for a
while and a lot of Deb Gordon's work was
with ants looking at ants and she's done
some uh pretty incredible research um
kind of looking at ant collectives
and this is something that she
writes Redwood
ant a colony of Redwood ants remembers
its trail system leading to the same
trees year after year although no single
ant
does in the forest of Europe they forg
high in trees and feed on excretions of
aphids another type of insect small
insect that in turn feeds on the tree
now their nests are enormous mounds of
pine needles situated in the same place
for decades occupied by many generations
of
colonies these colonies I can just
interject here some of these colonies
last a very long time they're very long
lifespans The Colony it does and the
colony outlasts the the individual ant
so e an e each ant tends to take the
same Trail every
day uh uh day after day to the same tree
during the long Winters the ants huddled
together under the snow and the Finnish
neologist Raina Rosen showed that when
an emerge in the spring an older ant
goes out with a younger ant uh along
that older ant's habitual Trail the
older ant dies and then the younger ant
adopts that trail as its own leading the
group leading the colony to remember or
reproduce the previous year's Trails so
you have this particular type of
connection between nodes if you will uh
connecting the memories from one
generation to the next year after year
all
the entire Colony so it's a a kind of
dionic uh a dionic connection if you
will so after going through all of those
Notions of memory I hope that's clear
that there different types of memory
that are occurring at different uh
temporal and spatial scales and those
temporal spatial scales can be kind of
demarcated by different levels of
biological
organization now we can ask the question
uh which one of these or which which of
these should I say are going to be you
know subject to cognitive explanation as
a cognitive process now when I say
subject to cognitive
explanation uh I want to make this
clear uh I'm asking the question which
of these particular types of memory
systems or uh exhibitions of memory that
we should be able to use cognitive
theories and cognitive Frameworks to try
to explore and understand now this is
not just for example using a cognitive
theory uh with scare Cotes is not an as
if explanation it's not using the
intentional stance uh but it's actually
using cognitive theories to think about
these uh and identify me these
mechanisms and functional the functional
placement of these particular types of
memory systems as cognitive
processes um so right away
I think it's quite obvious that we do
this with organisms that's that's going
to be the paradigmatic level of
biological organization at which we ask
these questions which we apply our which
apply our cognitive theories to our
cognitive Frameworks to in a
non-instrumental way but what about
cellular memory what about immune system
memory what about Collective
memory
um again we do this how are we going to
get uh and the question that I ask now
is how are we going to get uh any type
of uh how are we going to explore this
question uh because I think it's a it's
a it's an interesting question we can
make some assumptions and and just say
that there the perhaps there's a you
know similar principles running through
all of them uh given this particular
definition of or uh you know
characterization of memory from FTI
Booka and Mike L uh they all count as
memory so why not apply cognitive
theories to them I think there's some
that can lead us into some difficult
territory uh and if we do this
non-selectively and so I want to look at
now and introduce a particular type of
way of thinking about this that's going
we can kind of ring a particular type of
Criterion a rough Criterion out for
thinking about uh which which of these
biological organizational levels really
are warranted for this
now warranted uh to explain in terms of
uh cognitive explanations or warranted
targets for our cognitive
explanations one clue here is is going
to come from this particular kind of uh
you know passage from Pamela
lion uh and she
writes uh using actually I should I
should I should say something about this
uh this particular kind of definition
that she offers or again a character
ation that can be
changed uh she's offering something that
is very much influenced by Sarah
shuttleworth who's a cognitive ecologist
or cogn or cognitive ethologist excuse
me uh and this particular definition is
or characterization is quite I think
it's again it's General but it's General
enough to do some
work um specific enough to do some work
so cognition here comprises the sensory
and other information processing
mechanism
an organism has for becoming familiar
with valuing and interacting
productively with features of its
environment exploring exploiting evading
in order to meet its existential needs
now these are going to be the most basic
of which are are survival persistence
growth thriving and
reproduction now if we concentrate on
that the existential needs and saying
this is fundamental to
cognition uh we'll have various you know
we'll have various philosophers various
biologists various cognitive scientists
who will back this up U Matana and
verella are kind of the obvious ones
people coming from the kind of
autopoetic
Frameworks a poetic Theory people coming
from the
organizational uh biology theories for
example uh people coming from like like
honas for uh uh who thinks that you know
metabolism is the basis of meaningful
Behavior any type of
self-concern so any entity that has its
own metabolic machinery
is therefore uh this is going to be
Central to that entities having
capacities that are going to be subject
to cognitive
explanation another person philosopher
that's out there also who who really
emphasizes kind of metabolism and how it
kind of Shades into cognition is someone
like Peter gy
Smith
so uh one way to think about
metabolism is through the lens of what's
called a metabolic individual
um and this
is under the kind of under the larger or
more General type of uh kind of
biological philosophical philosophical
framework I suppose biology thinking
about what biological individuals are uh
and this is a question that's come up
for many many many years and one of the
kind of I think
fundamental uh books about this was
written by Julian Huxley Thomas H Thomas
Huxley uh his his grandson uh and
produced in released in
1912 um and it's quite interesting uh
you know Charles Darwin wrote a bit also
about the biological individual uh but
it wasn't until I think Julian huxley's
book that a lot of and he wrote this
when he was quite young I think he was
27 uh many interesting questions came
out he had a very interesting a keen a
sharp perspective on what the notion of
biological individuality is now what is
it it means when we're asking a question
about what a biological individual is uh
we want to provide an
account uh of what in the biological
World constitutes accountable and
relatively well delineated cohesive
unit so there two ways to go about
there's two general ways to go about
this there's more than two ways but I'll
just concentrate on two ways here uh you
can think about darwinian individuals
which are going to be units of
reproduction these are going to be any
type of units that are capable of uh
undergoing darwinian uh natural
selection uh which means they have to
have you know meet three criteria those
three criteria that you know lant was uh
you know expressed as you know
variation uh or her heritable
variation and selection so
uh it has to meet these criteria so you
have things like genes that could be a
darwinian individual or chromosomes that
could be a darwinian individual because
these are or memes ideas these are
things that can undergo darwinian
natural selection these are units
however there's another type of uh
biological individual that you typically
find in when theorizing about uh you
know various biological processes
various biological phenomena and this is
going to be the metabolic IND idual it's
going to be a unit of function that has
it and this unit is going to has it have
its own metabolic
Machinery um so let's look now just a
little bit more at metabolic
individuality I think you can understand
how this comes apart from darwinian
individuals and I'll try to make this
more
explicit
so uh according to Peter God
Smith uh metabolic individuals are
systems comprised of diverse parts which
work together to maintain the system
structure uh despite the turnover of
material by making use of sources of
energy and other resources from their
environment now diverse parts that
should stand out they're going to have
some type of cohesion that maintain the
structure of a
system uh they're going to be
essentially persists for things that
actually serve their own
self-maintenance
over time
things that use energy to resist the
forces of Decay or a force entropy only
contingently things that reproduce so
that metabolic individual does not have
to be a darwinian
individual that's quite important so you
have certain types of darwinian
individuals again a gene a gene is not a
metabolic individual a gene does not
have its own kind of metabolic Machinery
a gene is not a persister it doesn't
engage in the types of uh behaviors or
activities that keep keeps itself
going um and metabolic individuality is
a quite important concept when it comes
to thinking
about transitions in
individuality this notion is something
for many of you probably know about this
but it's a notion what it comes from
theoretical biology it's based
upon uh Loosely based upon veers from uh
the major transitions in evolution
uh that was kind of formalized by uh
John Mayer Smith and er Z maray and
these the idea about major transitions
in individuality we're thinking about
how one level of biological organization
reaches the next level of biological
organization over evolutionary time
scales and an example of this might be
for example uh an example for this would
be going from a proc cariot
uh to a eukaryotic cell the evolution of
from a Brar to eukaryotic cell or the
evolution from a eukaryotic cell a
single celled ukar to a multi-celled
ukar um and those those particular types
of transitions are quite important and a
lot of kind of biological theories are
you know are focused upon understanding
how those transitions uh occurred over
time what were the circumstances under
which they occur did they occur once did
they occur multiple times and many
different ways um so matter look at
individuality is interesting when
thinking about uh you know ukar
Genesis which is H how do you go from a
you know single a single cell
procaryotic
organism uh to a eukaryotic organism
with uh you know uh with a nucleus with
uh various kind of uh you know Cellular
Parts like a chloroplast or mitochondria
uh and the idea here is that there's
some type of metabolic integration most
of the theories that are thinking about
kind of ukog Genesis think about this in
terms of a metabolic integration where
two cells whether it's going to be a
bacteria an alpha bacteria and some type
of Aran are going to come together in
some way it's going to either be by you
know there different V various theories
one doesn't have to be committed to the
theory but looking at this particular
type of illustration you have some type
of fosis that's occurring from a larger
cell to the smaller cell uh when that
happens uh there's a depending upon the
natures of those two different types of
cells the the the the
inner Alpha bacteria or the and the kind
of the the outer uh what it's a going to
be an
ARCA depending upon that kind of
relationship they could enter into some
type of symbiotic relationship such that
the output of that uh endos symbient if
you will is something that's
metabolically useful for its external
environment which is another cell and
vice versa and so this nestedness of one
metabolic individual in
another after
time uh is going to you know evolve into
a single individual where those two
individuals that those two entities that
were at one point in time separate are
now so close knit metabolically that
they're one type of individual so you
have this idea that metabolic
individuals can be
nested uh and that's that's a quite
quite important idea here metabolic
individuality is going to come in
degrees also for this
reason so how might the notion of
metabolic individuality hint at what
cognitive
explanations uh of memory might get the
most
purchase I want to argue the following
uh if metabolic individuals are first
and foremost persists and such
self-maintenance is to be the
fundamental background against which all
cognitive capacities might be thought to
arise again this is an assumption then
the kind of memory learning decision-
making anticipation for that matter that
warrants possible cognitive explanation
qua cognitive process is going to be the
one that arises at the level of the
metabolic
individual now this automatically rules
out genes when we talk about Gene
learning or say Gene Gene regulatory
systems that are going to actually you
know be engaged in something like U you
know associative learning or
conditioning uh which there's some
research that shows this I think we can
say sure genes do learn but if that's
the case if Gene regulatory networks are
not metabolic individuals themselves I
think this is a kind of
a a misclassification if you will uh and
because Gene regulatory Networks work
within a metabolic
individual they're not the metabolic
individual
itself uh viruses for example uh viruses
are dependent upon their host for the
metabolism so these things are not going
to these types of entities are not going
to be metabolic
individuals uh and I think we kind of
have a have a basis for thinking about
this given the assumption that you know
uh metabolic individuals are persists
and that cognition first and foremost is
going to function directly for the
entity in which that those particular
kind of capacities are working for it's
going to function directly for the
self-maintenance of that
individual so since metabolic
individuality comes in
degrees uh an interesting kind of
question arises so how much metabolic
individuality is going to be required to
Warrant memory being subject to
cognitive explanation how much is too
little now again if you remember the
idea that I just said recently the the
idea I just brought up that you can have
cells within
cells uh you have a mitochondrium which
actually has its own has remnant of its
own DNA right now within uh any type of
somatic
cell uh and sematic cells within organs
and organs within you know organisms how
do we actually think about degrees of
metabolic individuality in this sense
that's
non-arbitrary um
so I want to argue that even if some
entity qualifies as a marginal metabolic
individual the fact that it's part of a
larger system which even has a higher
rank of metabolic individuality suggests
that the behavior of the organization
level that's the highest degree of
relative metabolic individuality is
going to be subject to the explanation
of cognitive memory or learning or
decision making so the highest degree of
metabolic individuality in a nest group
and nested system is going to require
actual applications of kind of cognitive
theories and cognitive Frameworks in a
way that's not instrumental or just
taking the you know the U intentional
stance so we can return to each of these
forms of
memory and and think about applying this
particular type of question applying
this particular type of
criteria so we already talked about or
organismal memory and I think if this is
the case then we can we can take that
off sure organisms are going to have the
highest relative degree of metabolic
individuality uh of their organizational
levels of all of the levels that they
actually are composed of and this is
going to you know be good news to the
notion of uh asking whether or not say
pham's externalized memory counts as
actual memory uh that should we should
be apping we can be asking uh you know
whether or not that type of memory if
it's navigational memory uh whether it
satisfies various uh types of conditions
that you know people thinking about
navigational memory would need to apply
to it to understand its function to
understand uh the mechanisms behind it
better what about cellular
memory uh I want to argue that cells
they have their own metabolic Machinery
I think that's quite
obvious and they're thus they're
metabolic individuals you know they
metabolize and they have means to
metabolize but relative to the metabolic
individuality of the
encompassing biological levels at which
you find sematic cells uh they're quite
low uh their
survival is dependent obviously upon
their EnV
environment but the metabolic
individuality and this is where you get
kind the the kind of marginal metabolic
individuality of kind of subotic cells
uh their maintenance is something that
is directed towards the maintenance of
the system of which they're a part so
when you get when you when you have you
know somatic cells or group symatic
cells uh whose maintenance is reshift
towards their own existence you start
having certain things like
tumors uh and this is like uh you know
metastasis things of that nature and I
think this is this is kind of turning
against this is you have a kind of
turning against uh this the system of
which they're apart they start using
that system uh and metabolizing that
system uh they become decoupled from
that system another way to think about
this is in terms of
autonomy when a cell has too much
autonomy when it regains its autonomy
from the system of which it's a part A
sematic Cell uh that cell actually
becomes delarius for the system so it's
not controlled by the system anymore so
I would like to say that something like
you know cellular memory uh we can use
the intentional stance to talk about it
maybe that'll get us somewhere but I
think to use something
non-instrumentally uh is it's actually a
conflation given uh given what again
given what uh the the different typ
types of Transitions and individuality
that have occurred over evolutionary
time scales have led to the dependencies
upon these different types of
organizational levels and differences in
autonomy uh so no I don't believe that's
the case uh that cellular memory should
be targeted with cognitive theories in
any non-instrumental way immune system
memory I think is the same thing really
the cells of an immune system they have
their own metabolic
machinery and a certain degree of
metabolic auton
sure
um long-term functioning of metabolic
processes and Persistence of the network
of immune specific cells and molecules
that make up an immune system are going
to be dependent upon their functional
integration with uh their functional
integration with an organism that
dependence upon that functional
organization is uh is it's something
that is to be
expected given where that where immune
system or the cells that make up the
immune system how are they related to
the larger the larger encompassing kind
of system so um relative to the organism
in which you find immune cells or immune
systems uh those immune cells are not
going to actually be more autonomous
than that system within which in there
with right so that's uh that in that
sense uh if you can start comparing
levels of autonomy in that sense you'll
have differences of course these are
happening the auton the actions the
behaviors if you will of these systems
are going to be having it on different
time scales however when you're just
kind of thinking about uh whether or not
the immune system could ever act in its
own accord or for its own
accord uh that's something that I think
uh gives you a kind of quite direct
answer as to whether or not immune
systems are going to be uh you know
targets for cognitive explanation which
I don't think they
are uh lastly a collective memory so the
at the level of something like a
colony
so uh here's three reasons why I think
an an Colony might be viewed as a
metabolic individual it's made up of
hetrogeneous Parts again uh you have
differentiation of colony members have
the queen of course the reproductive
function of the queen but then you have
workers uh which are all sisters um I
just like bees in the sense uh and they
have their all the functional
allocations you're going to have
different types of phenotypes within the
colony uh and they maintain a particular
Colonial structure uh that is going to
be dependent over the turnover of
individual
ants now there's the high degree of
metabolic integration between these
parts um uh different ants are going to
actually uh retrieve food and forage
Feed The Colony feed the nests feed the
feed the feed the queen
uh and that metabolic integration is
dependent upon each of the parts fitting
together and functioning together
cooperatively now there's going to be a
small degree of non-cooperation or uh
with within col within any Colony but
that's going to be overshadowed by a
Cooperative
behavior um lastly you have integration
uh which is going to be underwritten by
external signals like again phermones
and phone trails
uh and behavior so entering and exiting
the nest at a certain type of
rate uh so it really doesn't in this
case again uh like phum it really
doesn't matter if the signals are
internal or
external uh these these signals are
going to be used the way that they're
used again the way they function is
going to be analogous to internal
signals uh so is collective memory
subject to cognitive
explanation uh in a non-instrumental way
as a cognitive process I think assuming
that there isn't any type of system that
is in encompassing an ant
colony uh that scores higher than the
colony in terms of metabolic
individuality uh I think an an an ant
colony is going to be in this case where
it's going to be maybe equal to the
individual an on occasion this is this
is a dynamic obviously a dynamic process
uh but it's it might be equal to the
individual an the individual organism so
colonies come close having come close to
having a similar score enough to regard
them as something that we can ask the
question or apply literally cognitive
theories to an colonies and I think this
is the this this kind of butresses this
idea of colonial intelligence a colonial
memory Colonial
learning so that's that so in
summary um we can return to the question
of vum again that was the kind of feram
is our spring board here is it warranted
to interpret pham's use of extracellular
slime this mucco polysaccharide is a
form of biological memory I want to say
yes we're warranted in thinking about it
in terms of
memory can such a memory be investigated
from the perspective of cognitive memory
can we apply cognitive explanations to
it I'm going to say yeah sure
uh ferum is an organism organisms are
again parag gimatic forms of memory uh
me memory kind of um ex they exhibit
memory in a very paradigmatic way that
we've seen in uh with within the talk
and I believe that uh F obviously is
going to be a metabolic individual for
that reason so we can ask the third
question is external L spatial memory a
form of cognition
uh and I say
perhaps I I'll leave it at that perhaps
because this is going to depend again if
we can apply cognitive theories
specifically navigational theories of
memory uh and learning to forum's case
because it is the highest degree has the
highest degree of metabolic individual
individuality of its biological
organizational
levels uh that's going to depend upon
the different types of navigational
theories that we apply
so that third question is going really
be it's going to be Theory dependent
it's going to be framework dependent
whether or not that's going to happen uh
melan for
example uh he suggested that these are
three different types of criteria for
spatial memory or navigational memory
you have to have survival relevant
storage which means that information
that gets stored is going to be
determined by the relevance of that
information to the survival of the
individual now that again goes very well
with the idea of a metabolic individual
and a
persister uh number two for something to
qualify spatial memory there has to be
instability over time so uh the obvious
way to think about this is memories can
be
forgotten they can be overwritten a
memory that can't be overwritten no
matter what type of substrate that
memory is in uh doesn't seem to be
something like a
memory uh it it can't it can't the it
doesn't have the Dynamics of a
memory uh and lastly there's something
like meta memory He suggests that you
know spatial memory or navigational
memory should should be should be core
this this a core feature of it which
just means that there are other
processes that are going to influence
whether memory states are AC or
ignored uh in favor of guiding Behavior
with uh the current
context and whether or not these all are
by ferum this is a question but now we
get to the the point where we can ask
these specific types of questions from a
cognitive theory apply it to a
particular type of individual because
that individual seems to uh you know
kind of it seems to be a kind of the
highest degree of met have the highest
degree of metabolic
individuality a relative degree of
metabol metabolic
individuality so uh in conclusion
regardless of whether pham's use of
extracellular slime is considered a
cognitive process or not you know again
that's going to be Theory dependent it
should be clear that focusing on the
behavior of the single cell non-
neuronal organism is going to be quite
helpful and revealing interesting and
important questions about memory and it
can help us consider relations between
different forms of biological memory so
uh again if cognition is first and
foremost a biological process and
biological organism
uh approaching this particular this this
idea of cognitive explanations using
non- neuronal model organisms like
theerum it's going to offer a really
promising way I think uh of going
forward a potential escape from the trap
or the you know the prison of our own
kind of familiarity and I think that's a
really important thing as to have model
organisms that are so different from us
that it stretches the imagination if you
will but stretches the imagination in
ways that you know uh expands our
Horizons and the types of the different
types of questions we can ask and that
help us to kind of reflect on our own
case or cases that are more similar to
us thank
you thank
you
awesome all right well while uh some
people may be writing any questions in
the live chat I believe the
previous time we discussed was in live
stream 30 it was how to count biological
Minds symbiosis the free energy
principle and reciprocal multiscale
integration so some of those topics
definitely came back into play ranging
from the metabolic symbiosis and and the
multiscale nesting where do you see
active inference and the free energy
principle in this line of research
well I think I think it's an interesting
way to model this this most certainly
interesting way to model it and I think
the particular
idea
of uh taking metabolism and taking
different levels of metabolic
integration
seriously is something that
uh I don't
know it's something that I wasn't really
I was thinking about it previously in
how to count biological mind how to
count IAL lli yes but
um I didn't really understand the
importance of this as an evolutionary
process as as the importance to it as
being kind of the result of an
evolutionary process and once you have
these taking this into
consideration uh it uh you do have a a
manner
of a manner of kind of delineating where
the targets going to be or where where
the most important targets going to be
so you can apply for example active
inference to any
level you can apply it to any level uh
but some levels are going to be more
interesting than
others and I think uh because it is a
type of you know active it's a type of
process Theory and it's a type of kind
of modeling framework uh it's you're
free to kind of choose which levels you
want to you want to apply it to however
there are going to be some levels that
are going to be more
um should I say this they're going to
they're going to actually have more of a
payoff when you start applying other
types of cognitive theories
to I think particularly when you start
thinking about uh uh not literally
nesting but I would say contextualizing
those theories within something like uh
you know uh thinking about major
transitions in cognitive Evolution or
you thinking about major
transitions more generally uh but
cognitive theories putting putting like
that those those particular types of
cognitive theories in the context of uh
you know Evolution if if one thinks
about cognition as being something a
kind of Suite or a toolbox of various
capacities that have
evolved and one doesn't just you know
take on the
Assumption uh that you know all life is
cognitive which some people do but then
that question becomes whether or not you
know it's not a question about how
cognition evolved necessarily but uh
it's a question about how life evolved
those two questions become the same
question yeah awesome like the cognitive
turn in evolutionary
biology leads us almost to the point of
asking well
what remains other than cognitive
account is the vend diagram of the
cognitive accounts if we take it down to
the materials
level or ultimately identical with the
biological account like es or or the
metabolic all of the substrate of living
systems is part of the building up and
breaking down of
metabolism so then you know what what is
outside of that scope like how how many
different frames and and and maybe no
need to reduce to one but point to the
the the um same cell in in the petri
dish um I'll ask a question in the live
chat okay Gia maximalist wrote thank you
how do you think the metabolism of
different sized organisms relates to
their perception of time or their own
behavior it's an interesting really
interesting question
um I think metabolism can run in an
organism and I'm quite
sure I would be quite sure about this CL
metabolism can
run uh without an organism being
necessarily aware of
anything it's at a certain level that we
can actually have a particular type of
uh like understanding if you will of our
metabolism but metabolism nonetheless
will
affect uh will affect perception it will
affect uh kind of how organisms behave
uh and it will affect probably uh their
Pro
preception uh and uh depending upon uh
because it's it's about kind of value
tradeoffs if you will so uh if
metabolism for example if if if if an
organism is uh in a state that where
metabolism is the function of metabolism
is breaking down there going to be
certain type of you know stress
responses that
occur that will affect the manner in
which an organism behaves that's quite
that's quite simple uh at which level an
organism actually is aware that that's
happening that's a different question
and I'm not I'm not sure exactly where
that happens that you have to have a
quite complex uh neuronal system for
that to happen but even before you get
to that complex neuronal system
uh you know complex nervous system even
a brain you're going to have certain
types of mechanisms in place that are
going to be able to uh bring an organism
back into its homeostatic range that
bringing it back into that homeostatic
range is uh as something that I would be
very certain that most organisms if not
all organisms have to do in order to
Rive cool also there's interesting
connection ctions like with the
metabolic individuality you focused on
that primary persistence and then even
molecules or processes that are thought
of as almost reaching into the Semitic
like
neurotransmitters sometimes are amino
acids or just several modifications away
so the line between what's uh metabolite
and what is a a
semiochemical they are also overlapping
because metabolites are key signaling
molecules um yeah maybe just to your
book like what do you hope the impact of
such a book is or H how did you come to
think we need a slime mold and
philosophy book and who would read it
and think
what yeah
well I I was quite lucky at one point in
time uh I got in touch with Mike
Lin and Mike uh was you really he's he's
Michael is fantastic
person brilliant guy and it's fantastic
person and he like ask me okay like
you've been writing a little bit about
you know ferum you've been writing about
s have have you got your hands dirty yet
have you started doing experiments I'm
like no not at all I said like okay well
let's let's change that so Mike sent me
some protocol for culturing for zerum
and took me step by
step uh with a lot of a lot of
communication with him as to how to do
this and how to set up some experimental
designs I had been you
know uh about year and a half prior to
that I was over in Rome with giovan pulo
uh learning how to design uh kind of
Behavioral experiments
and how Mike was the one that kind of
like you know reshift my focus from you
know human behavioral experiments to
behavioral experiments in a p dis and
the more I got doing the these
particular types of experiments nothing
published not not anything yet anyway um
uh the more I was thinking about what an
incredible way to kind of uh ask or
answer questions that a lot of a lot of
questions that have been happening or
arising in kind of theoretical biology
or philosophy of
biology you just don't you don't you
know there are a lot of what ifs a lot
of contrafactual a lot of you know
speculation that happens uh but given
the ease with which this particular type
of organism can be cultivated or
cultured given uh the speed at which it
moves and also uh you know given the
what actually can do it's quite unique
as to what it can actually uh the
behavior that it engages in uh there are
a lot of things that you can proceed to
a lot of questions that you can proceed
to ask and just answer uh and so I
haven't had the
time uh or necessarily the
resources to sit down for five years and
answer all these questions myself with
people in the lab um but uh at BAM uh R
University I was given the chance to
work with a couple people uh one is her
name is uh true rang and she's uh she's
a post off there and she's doing she was
working on kind of
um uh recording climbing
plants and doing analysis of climbing
plant
um uh kind of climbing plant
Behavior Uh I don't know if you've seen
of course you've seen kind of recordings
of plant tendrils as they kind of grow
and wrap around Vines they wrap their
kind of tendrils around certain poles
and things like this and she was doing
uh kinematic analysis of that and we
decided to actually uh use that same
type of
analysis with ferum uh looking at its
growth looking at its movement uh and in
response to certain things so uh I was
very very very very lucky to uh make her
acquaintance and be able to work with
her um but I thought okay well prior to
this there's no way that I can do this
myself or all of it myself it's an
intensive it's a really intensive
research program there's so many
questions that can be asked and I think
part of the part of the fun of it uh and
I think part of the value of it is
asking the questions and maybe inspiring
people who want to want to answer these
questions in the lab uh to give give
give them a couple kind of questions to
kind of uh you know to use as a fcr if
you will uh and to get philosophers of
biology philosophers philosophers of C
science uh and biologists
microbiologists together in one
space uh to work together and perhaps
think about these questions and and use
resources uh you know to answer these
questions if you will uh in a laboratory
setting and so that's what the book is
about pretty much it's like it's looking
at
Alum which is like it's it's an organism
that I'm absolutely you know I'm I
continue to be mesmerized by you know uh
the the various things that it can do
and just how how beautiful of of a life
cycle it has uh and interesting of a
life cycle that it has uh how it can be
used to answer some questions from very
very long-standing questions in the
philosophy of biology and say philosophy
of cognitive science
also awesome that res resonates a lot
I'll add a few points I'll begin with a
quote from a 1989 paper a framework for
plant Behavior by Silvertown and Gordon
who you quoted and they wrote there's
some question whether words used to
describe animal behavior such as the
word Behavior itself or foraging can be
properly applied to the activities of
plants so it's kind of this Evergreen
discussion oh okay but is it really
solving that maze or or is it really
memory and certainly Mike Levin and and
others and these come up like is
anything that's outside of the
organismal frame actually doing
cognition and then the slime mold blurs
that because it's also a single cell so
then it's like well why would it matter
if there's a lipid membrane separating
this or that when the cell is also the
organismal boundary and then also to the
relevance and sort of the cross
fertilization of philosophy of biology
and the behavioral sciences or ethology
in Professor Gordon's undergraduate
class one thing that she would have the
undergraduates do was design and carry
out a behavioral experiment even you
know do squirrels cross the bike path
more on Wednesdays
and there's something about doing any
inquiry that provides philosophical
insights that that the armchair
doesn't and it helps reveal there's a
associative
analogical mode that's like studying
foraging across different systems
however by virtue of thinking and
scoping over so many systems most are
not going to be directly engaged with
you know we're thinking about like a
space hypothetical asteroid forager and
um ants as a broad category but then
when you get into the natural history
and the Behavioral Science or the
constraints of a specific
laboratory just sticking with one system
like a dropa or slime mold or this one
field site those can offer so many
questions that even leads to reinter
ation of what the bigger category like
navigation was so for example like in
the in the navigation example or the
maze solving I thought well it's doing
something spatial but not necessarily
with a cognitive
map so
right what is does now it's like hm so
actually there's some play between what
is cognition that's realized spatially
and that which is aware of its own
spatiality and that's something that can
just
be brought to bear with a petri dish and
some experiments like that so it's
just when the philosophy questions are
held up with the
inquiry there's just amazing
possibilities and like you're what you
shared shows that you know people come
from both sides and and um may it be a
perforated membrane between the two
because there's so much to like learn on
both sides Absolut absolutely absolutely
I think this like you hit the nail on
the head it's just
um I take it then that you were you were
in uh Deborah's Gordon's class then did
you take courses for her she was my PhD
adviser ah of course fantastic that make
sense makes a lot of she she's
incredible she's really incredible um so
yeah I I think that you you hit the nail
or the head with many many of the things
that you just said um in terms of say
spatial
navigation uh yeah ferum not going to
have a cognitive map not going to have a
cognitive map and this is I think like a
I think cognitive maps are quite complex
things that there's still disagreements
as to whether or not you know uh which
organisms use cognitive Maps
uh again Sarah shuttleworth
2014 she really kind of puts the breakes
on and say if you can explain this a lot
of what organisms do animals do she's a
she's an
ethologist uh in terms of using certain
types of uh you know other simpler
mechanisms uh that they're still they're
still quite complex cognitively but they
simpler mechanisms in comp Maps uh
running computations on comp Maps um uh
you have you have these things going on
in ants for example where you have like
entric or versus allocentric kind of
recognition of landmarks and things of
that nature or um you probably know this
the term better than me but dead
reckoning uh using dead reckoning dead
reckoning is distinct from using a
cognitive map it probably can be used in
addition in animals with cognitive Maps
uh but the question then arises in phum
is there something similar to dead reing
happening is there something similar to
Landmark navigation happening is it
leaving its own Landmark something like
this you can ask these question start to
ask these questions uh because you can
relate Its
Behavior Uh to other types of cognitive
theories if you have the right if you're
asking the right level if you're at the
right level you know uh so yeah it's not
going to satisfy any any of the kind of
Criterion if you will for thinking about
cognitive Maps but maybe Landmark use
perhaps you know Landmark use does not
necessarily have to be a personal
process it can be a subpersonal
process I think it's a pader quote like
computers don't play chess they do
statistics but they don't do statistics
they just follow the laws of physics and
all of that it's like cognitive
phenomena when we start to really
interrogate them and break them apart oh
well that outfielder is not
really inferring the location of the
ball they're just using a behavioral
heris to stand where it's going to it's
like well if that's actually how it's
done then what is the space
between the problem as it was set up and
how it's really being done in all these
different biological ways so and that
even came up in the reciprocal
integration like what do we
expect what are we surprised by
what what does what we're surprised by
say about who and how we think we are in
how we analyze these cognitive
systems um I'll ask a last last uh
question from the live chat upcycle Club
wrote how might the Adaptive behaviors
of slime molds contribute to our
understanding of distributed cognition
okay that's a good that's a good
question I think it relates back to I
would
have I would have to say really very
important work by Chris Reed uh and his
colleagues over at mcer University the
first paper that I referred to you to
the 2012 paper about externalized
spatial memory uh or externalized
navigational memory is I think that's a
good place to start with that in terms
of uh an organism that uses its own
byproducts to
navigate uh it uses its own
byproducts uh you know again this is not
this is not a personal level kind of
choice or anything like this but I
should say this I think this is quite
important in terms of understanding the
nature of it once we get to say okay
well this is the right level for looking
at memory this is perhaps the right
level for looking at the organismal
level or biological organizational level
for thinking about things like problem
solving decision making and so on and so
forth its use of extracellular slime
which again is a mucco
polysaccharide it can be
overridden so it's not just a repulsion
to this
stuff uh if you create a situation in a
Petri dish where you have a circle of
extra this is one of the experiments
I've done and you put a pharum in that
Circle uh and then you put a reasonably
sized oat flake which that's something
that you use as kind of um
uh it's for food in order for
motivation um it will it'll climb over
the Excell line it'll and that's one of
the things that I think is quite
important uh and thinking about and that
was one of the kind of criteria also
about kind of spatial memory or
navigational memory uh that was brought
up in the talk uh that something can be
overridden given the particular type of
context I would think there are many
other ways that you can expand this when
you can ask the question when does it
use this extra slim and what does it use
EXT extracellular sign for is it is it
just uh you know again is it just a a
lubricant for uh motility no we know
that kind of uses it for navigation what
in what ways does it use it for
navigation and does it always have to be
in contact with it is are there
gradients or there there many questions
that could be asked but the I guess the
most important thing to think about is
the fact that whatever is going on it's
it's a coupling of a cell to Something
in its external
milu and depending upon the
geometry of that extracellular SL
depending upon the values of various
stimuli within its surrounds that it can
sense again it's it's it's sensing these
various it's sensing food for example uh
through concentration gradients
uh and through AAR that are going
through the AAR whether it's going to be
oats or sugar from oats that are kind of
leaking sleeping into the AAR or whether
it's in its own natural
environment uh it can do this particular
Ty these I'll call them computations if
you will on uh what's available and
what's more
important uh for this particular type of
context uh and exor slime plays a plays
a role in that in the sense
that uh it's one of the things that it
weighs in these particular types of
computations now the computations again
might be very very very very
simple uh but there their computations
that are being run because it's in the
integration of
information and the weighing out of this
information according to uh according to
kind of the continuation of metabolic
functioning when things don't work out
then it goes into one of these dormant
stages and can reemerge after waiting
things out but that's uh extracellular
slime plays a very very important role
so again the suggestion look at the work
of Chris Reed um read it Al 2012 2013
and it's a very good starting place to
understand how ferum uses extracellular
Slim in these
ways I'm also struck by when you showed
the life cycle diagram and how it seems
like less is known about what cognitive
tasks or work is done in those other
stages and then also how different they
looked from a size and
morphology and it just is like
what what we you know the the
caterpillar and the larvae and the
Butterfly all do different things and so
when we think about the life cycle
perspective and communic there's so
many cool ways to go well if you have
any last comments please go for it
otherwise it's a great direction of
research and it's exciting to see how
the cognitive Sciences are entering the
chat and bringing a lot of excitement to
these perennial questions about
individuality and
cognition I think so much yeah I think
in terms of life cycles I think there's
something fun that um and and very
important that goes on uh one of the
things that has uh beset I said I
suppose biological research a lot of
biological research and specifically you
know thinking about
cognition is that we're adults
interests uh we think about the adult
organism you know of course there's
development of psychology and kind of
people are looking at that but most a
lot of the research when we're talking
about generalizing certain types of
capacities of generalizing certain type
of uh you know uh response
rates uh we have a very kind of narrow
band of model organisms and ages of
model organisms that we're looking at uh
this even when you look at an organism
with a complex life
cycle uh you expand that in such an
incredible way because you're not just
looking at different ages you're looking
at different uh really really different
phenotypes within the same
organism over over over time and not
only are you looking at different
phenotypes uh you're looking at and this
is one of the things that I approach in
the book It's a Wonderful way to explore
something like nich
construction uh because if those
different parts of the life cycle are
responses to changes in the environment
their responses to various selection
pressures uh ways to accommodate
selection pressures sometimes they might
happen uh they might be primed by
certain types of stimuli sometimes not
uh then you have a different kind of
frame uh that one can use to think about
Niche construction various types of
Niche construction and how they're
related so yeah a beaver the you know
the stereotypical example of the beaver
building and that
uh to kind of control the Dynamics
within its particular type of
Niche uh you have that like that's a
particular type of externalized n
construction uh but then you have other
things which involve for example uh an
organism changing its own
morphology uh as a way to kind of uh
buffer itself from changes in selection
pressures harder selection pressure so a
change change in a change in temperature
it might be a change in for example
moisture so the mix amoeba can you know
it will will
synthesize fella by flatulate if there's
if it if it starts
raining if there's a lot of water then
those those it'll stop synthesizing
those fella and start falling again as
an amoeba as uh if if it dries out again
right and there's there kind of costs
like the costs of that particular type
of morphological change or that type of
Niche
construction are quite interesting
things to think about because when it's
uh a
bagate uh there it's it can't
reproduce so there's a trade-off there
when it's a mix amiba when it's
reproducing it can't
feed so uh there there very interesting
way to think about a life history
tradeoffs plus Niche construction and
and you get all of that with an if you
focus rather than on just the just the
plasmodium cell that we've been talking
about during this that we've been
focusing on on this talk on entire life
cycle and there many other organisms uh
Brites for example
ferns uh you know incredible incredible
life cycles that you know they behavior
is different in and and obviously in in
bof fights or or plants or whatever but
but the the same goes for them in the
sense that uh you have that that life
cycle provides a really beautiful way a
beautiful lens through which to see uh
how an individual's morphology is very
much coupled in in in incredible ways to
different environmental Dynamics and how
it can actually influence those Dynamics
and influence its own evolution
epic okay thank you Matt for joining
again and looking forward to reading the
book and till next
time thanks man bye right